CURRICULUM VITAE

Michael L. Treglia, Ph.D.

Urban Spatial Planner The Nature Conservancy, NYC Program 322 Eighth Ave, 16th Floor New York, NY 10001

Phone: +1-646-647-2045
E-mail: michael.treglia@tnc.org
Website: http://mltconsecol.github.io/

Research Interests

My research is focused on identifying strategies for biodiversity conservation while advancing analytical techniques and our understanding of ecology. I integrate methods from statistics, GIS, and remote sensing to study landscape-scale patterns and processes, often learning new skills and working closely with collaborators. My research has largely focused on anthropogenic threats to herpetofauna, though I am interested in extending my work to other taxa and entire ecosystems.

Education

2009-2014	Ph.D., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2007-2010	M.S., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2004-2007	B.S., Natural Resources, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.

Research Experience

2016-Pres	Urban Spatial Planner. Focused on understanding dynamics of open space in New York City
	using GIS and Remote Sensing data, and quantifying the roles that open space plays for native
	ecosystems and people. Supervisor: Ms. Emily Maxwell, The Nature Conservancy.

- 2014-2016 **Postdoctoral Scholar.** Focused on understanding relationships between environmental variability across multiple scales and biodiversity; working as part of the Oklahoma NSF-EPSCoR Program. Supervisor: Dr. Ron Bonett, University of Tulsa.
- 2009-14 **Dissertation.** Title: *Conservation of the endangered Arroyo Toad across multiple scales.* Five chapters focused on identifying threats to, and conservation opportunities for, the Arroyo Toad (*Anaxyrus californicus*). Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.
- Master's Thesis. Title: A translocated population of the St. Croix Ground Lizard: Analyzing its detection probability and investigating its impacts on the local prey base. Four chapters focused on understanding the ecology of the endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Ameiva polops), and examining effects of the species' detectability on monitoring. Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.
- 2007 **Research Assistant.** Collected field data for a long-term study on relationships between forestry management, coarse woody debris, and biodiversity. Supervisor: Dr. Stephen Morreale, Cornell University.
- 2005-07 **Research Assistant.** Maintained collection of live reptiles for research and teaching, including over 40 venomous snakes and lizards. Supervisor: Dr. Harry Greene, Cornell University.

- NSF-REU Intern. Conducted undergraduate research on reptiles and amphibians of St. Vincent, Lesser Antilles, resulting in four publications. Supervisor: Dr. Robert Powell, Avila University.
- 2005 **Urban Park Ranger for NYC Dept. of Parks and Recreation.** Conducted public outreach and led educational programs in New York City parks as a summer employee.
- 2004-05 **Lab Assistant.** Set up soil samples for chemical analysis with gas chromatograph. Supervisor: Dr. Joseph Yavitt, Cornell University.
- 2003-04 **Intern**. Bred poison dart frogs and analyzed effects of different diets on growth and development rates of the tadpoles. This research was submitted to Intel Science Talent Search Competition. Supervisor: Ms. Cathy Eser, Staten Island Zoo.
- 2002-04 **Intern.** Collected field data on pond turtles in New York for long-term research projects. Supervisor: Mr. David Karrmann, American Museum of Natural History.

Fellowships, Grants, and Awards

- 2013-14 Tom Slick Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$25,000.
- Willie May Harris Fellowship for Outstanding Teaching Assistants, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$12,000.

 E. E. Williams Research Grant, The Herpetologists' League. \$1,000.

Sylvia Scholarship, Mensa Foundation. \$600.

- 2012, 2013 Travel Grants, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Program at Texas A&M. \$675; \$700.
- 2010-12 NSF-IGERT Traineeship for the Applied Biodiversity Science Doctoral Program at Texas A&M University. \$84,000.
- 2009 Outstanding Master's Student, Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University.
- 2008 2nd Place for Talk, "An Invasive Anole, *Anolis sagrei*, on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles." Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
- 2007-08 Regents Graduate Fellowship, Texas A&M University. \$15,000.

2007 Ullman Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.

Arthur H. and Karin A. Nelson Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.

Publications (In Review and In Prep. Manuscripts are available upon request)

- 9. Fitzgerald, L.A., **M.L. Tregli**a, N. Angeli, T.J. Hibbitts, D.J. Leavitt, A.L. Subalusky, I. Lundgren, and Z. Hillis-Starr. 2015. Determinants of successful establishment of a new population of the critically endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Teiidae: *Ameiva polops*). *Restoration Ecology.* DOI: 10.1111/rec.12248
- 8. **Treglia, M.L.**, R.N. Fisher, and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2015 Integrating potential and current species distribution models to identify conservation opportunities for an endangered toad. *PLoS ONE*. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0131628
- 7. Wang, H.H., C.L. Wonka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins, W.E. Rogers. 2015. Species distribution modeling of an endangered endemic orchid, *Spiranthes parksii* (Correll). *AoB Plants*. DOI: 10.1093/aobpla/plv039

- 6. **Treglia, M.L.**, J. Valiulis, D. J. Leavitt, and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2013. Establishment of the Puerto Rican Ground Lizard (*Ameiva exsul*: Teiidae), on St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands: a threat to native fauna. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 47(2-3): 373-378.
- 5. Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2011. Translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard to Buck Island Reef National Monument, St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands. Pp. 109-115. In. Soorae P.S. (ed.) (2011). Global Reintroduction Perspectives: 2011. More case studies from around the globe. Gland, Switzerland: IUCN/SSC Re-introduction Specialist Group and Abu Dhabi, UAE: Environment Agency-Abu Dhabi. Xiv +250 pp.
- 4. **Treglia, M.L.**, O. Ramirez. 2009. *Nerodia rhombifer*. Geographic distribution. *Herpetological Review* 40(2):238.
- 3. **Treglia, M.L.**, A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, and J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. 2008. An invasive anole, *Anolis sagrei* on St. Vincent and its potential impact on native anoles. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 44(2):251–256.
- 2. Henderson, R.W., **M.L. Treglia**, and S.D. Powell. 2008. *Corallus cookii*. Foraging. *Herpetological Review* 38(4):466.
- 1. Powell, S.D., **M.L. Treglia**, R.W. Henderson, and R. Powell. 2007. Treeboas in the West Indies: responses of *Corallus cookii* and *C. grenadensis* to disturbed habitats. Pp. 374–387 in: R. W. Henderson and R. Powell (eds.). *Biology of the Boas and Pythons*. Eagle Mountain Publ., Utah.
- In Review Schaffer-Smith, D, D.Y. Maguire, S.A. Tomscha, **M.L. Treglia**, K.J. Jarvis, and J. Liu. Network analysis as a tool for quantifying the spatial, temporal, and cross-scale dynamics of telecoupled systems: an example using global soybean trade. Submitted to *Ecology and Society*. **Treglia, M.L.**, A.C. Landon, G.T. Kyle, R.N. Fisher, L.A. Fitzgerald. Multi-scale effects of land cover conditions on a riparian habitat specialist. Submitted to *Landscape Ecology*.
- In Prep. **Treglia, M.L.**, S.D. Martin, A.L. Boardman, R.M. Bonett. Does habitat stability promote the loss of a complex life cycle stage in a stream-associated salamanders? Target Journal: *Functional Ecology*.
 - **Treglia, M.L.** and L.A. Fitzgerald. A field experiment on the effects of an active-foraging lizard on its invertebrate prey base. Target Journal: *Journal of Zoology*.

Technical Reports and Other Publications

- Treglia, M.L. 2015. An Introduction to GIS Using QGIS (v. 2.6.1). Training material for QGIS, available at: http://mltconsecol.github.io/QGIS-Tutorial/.
- Treglia, M.L. 2014. Results of surveys for the endangered Arroyo Toad (*Anaxyrus californicus*) in 2013. *Annual Report to the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and California Department of Fish and Wildlife*.
- Daut, E. F., K. Dennis, E. Gómez-Ruiz, Z. Hurst, K. A. Roach, A. N. Santos, D. Toledo, **M. L. Treglia**, C. J. van Riper, and M. A. Wood. 2013. Reaching toward outward accountability of environmental non-governmental organizations. *Applied Biodiversity Sciences Perspectives Series* **3**:1-6.
- Treglia, M. L. and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 The translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard, Ameiva polops, to Buck Island Reef National Monument. Final Report to the National Park Service, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and Virgin Islands Department of Planning and Natural Resources.

- **Treglia, M. L.** and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 Population estimation of the St. Croix ground lizard, *Ameiva polops*, on Protestant Cay and Ruth Cay, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands. Final *Report to the United States Fish and Wildlife Service (Cooperative Agreement 401917J125)*.
- **Treglia, M.L.** 2006. An annotated checklist of the amphibians and reptiles of St. Vincent, West Indies. *Iguana* 13: 252–263.

<u>Oral Presentations</u> (* indicates Invited Presentation)

- Treglia, M.L., L.A. Alleman, E.N. Maxwell. Planning urban landscapes for people and pollinators: exploratory work in New York City. *Annual Meeting of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Baltimore, MD.*
 - **Treglia, M.L.**, D. Schaffer-Smith, D. Maguire, S. Tomscha, J. Liu. Application of network analysis for quantifying dynamics of telecoupled systems: an example using global soy trade. *Annual Meeting of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Baltimore, MD.*
- Wang, H-H, C.L. Wonkka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins and W.E. Rogers. Edaphic determinants of the distribution of an endangered terrestrial orchid: using Maxent as an investigative tool for rare plant conservation. *Texas Plant Conservation Conference, Biennial Meeting, Fort Worth, Texas.*
- Treglia, M.L., A. Mathews, and D. Wilson. Development of LiDAR-Based Data Products for Oklahoma. *Oklahoma Remote Sensing Workshop, Norman, OK.*
 - *Treglia, M.L. Landscape-Scale Approaches Guide Conservation and Inform Ecology in a Complex World. *Lecture to the Anthropology Department at the University of Tulsa*.
 - **Treglia, M.L.**, S.D. Martin, A.L. Boardman, and R.M. Bonett. Multi-scale influences of environmental variability on life history strategies of the Oklahoma salamander. *World Congress of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Portland, OR.*
- Wang, H.-H., C.L. Wonkka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins, and W.E. Rogers. Determinants and likelihood of occurrence of an endangered endemic orchid (Spiranthes parksii (Correll)) in central Texas. *Texas Plant Conservation Conference*, *Austin*, *TX*.
 - ***Treglia, M.L.** Multi-Scale Conservation in an Altered Landscape: The Case of the Endangered Arroyo Toad in Southern California. *Department of Biological Science, The University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK.*
 - **Treglia, M.L.** and G.T. Kyle. Estimating effects of land cover at multiple scales on habitat for the endangered arroyo toad. In J. Franklin, J.M. Sierra-Diaz, and L. Sweet (Chairs), *Impacts of Global Change: Linking Across Scales*. Symposium presented at the *Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Anchorage, AK*.
- Treglia, M.L. and R.N. Fisher. Integrating Historic and Current Distribution Models of an Endangered Species to Benefit Conservation. *Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Austin, TX.*
 - *Treglia, M.L. Conservation of the Endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard. *Lecture to Aggies for the Protection of Endangered Species at Texas A&M University.*
- *Treglia, M.L. Manifold GIS: Exploring the Capabilities of an Alternative GIS Package. *U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center San Diego Field Station. San Diego, CA.*Treglia, M.L. Anthropogenic Disturbances and Conservation of Endangered Amphibians in a Semi-arid Landscape: A Proposal Talk. *12th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.*

Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of an Insular Lizard Translocation on the Local Invertebrate Assemblage. *Annual Meeting of the Ecological Society of America, Pittsburgh, PA.*Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Impacts of a Translocated Lizard on an Island Arthropod

Assemblage. 11th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of Detectability on Lizard Population Estimates.

 Annual Meeting of the Southwestern Association of Naturalists, Monterrey, Nuevo Leon, MX.
- Treglia, M.L. The Translocation of an Extirpated Lizard in the Caribbean: A Proposal Talk. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

 Treglia, M.L., A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. An Invasive Anole: Anolis sagrei on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

Poster Presentations (†indicates Mentored Student)

- †Mohanty, R.P. and **M.L. Treglia**. Modeling the Current and Future Distributions of *Juniperus virginiana* Across the Continental United States. *Oklahoma NSF-EPSCoR Annual Conference, Norman, OK*
 - **Treglia, M.L.**, S.D. Martin, A.L. Boardman, and R.M. Bonett. Does Habitat Stability Promote the Loss of a Complex Life Cycle in a Stream-Associated Salamander? *Oklahoma NSF-EPSCoR Annual Conference, Norman, OK*
 - **Treglia, M.L.** and M.E. Young. Utilizing Patch Metrics to Improve Classification of Remote Sensing Imagery. *World Congress of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Portland, OR.*
- Lovette, J. T. Chang, **M.L. Treglia**, T. Gan, J. Duncan. Assessing Ecohydrological Impacts of Forest Disturbance Using Open Source Software. *Annual Meeting of the American Geophysical Union, San Francisco, CA*.
- Treglia, M.L. and A.C. Landon. Integrative Research for Biodiversity Conservation and Water Resource Management. Student Conference on Conservation Science New York. New York, NY.
 Treglia, M.L. and R.N. Fisher. Presence-Only Modeling to Understand the Historic Distribution of an Endangered Toad. 7th World Congress of Herpetology. Vancouver, BC, Canada
- Treglia, M.L. Conserving an Endangered Toad in a Dynamic Landscape. 1st Annual NSF-IGERT Online Competition. Available online at: http://www.igert.org/posters2011/posters/94
- Treglia, M.L. Effects of Detectability on Population Estimates of the Ground-Dwelling Lizard, Ameiva polops. 10th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

Teaching Experience

- 2016 Instructor for *Landscape Analysis and Modeling*, University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK.
- Instructor for *Graduate Seminar on Spatial Ecology*, University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK. Instructor for *Landscape Analysis and Modeling*, University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK.
- Half-day course on QGIS, as part of the Open Source for Open Science Workshop for the Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Program, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
- 2010, 2013 TA for *Herpetology*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
- Guest Lecturer for class, *Recreation Management of Wildlands*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
- 2007, 2012 TA for *Natural History of the Vertebrates*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
- TA for *Fundamentals of Ecology Lab*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.

Service

2005-06

2004-06

2014-16	Reviewer for E.E. Williams Research Grant Program, The Herpetologists' League.
2011-12	Co-Chair of the 13th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
2010-11	Treasurer of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
2009-10	President of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
	Web-Designer for the $11^{ m th}$ Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
	Judge for Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
2007-08	Mentor for Undergraduate Research at Texas A&M University, supervised by Dr. Lee
	Fitzgerald.
2006-07	President of the Cornell Herpetological Society.

Reviewer for the following journals: African Journal of Herpetology; Applied Herpetology; Biological Invasions; Ecological Modeling; Herpetologica; Herpetological Conservation and Biology; Herpetological Review; Journal of Applied Ecology; Journal of Biogeography; PeerJ.

Member of the following organizations: Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles; U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology.

Active member of the following software listserves: QGIS-User List (QGIS); R-Sig-Geo (R Spatial). **Contributor to the following R Packages:** pgirmess (available on CRAN); Rfrag (available at the Fragstats Website); iButtonDataOrganizer (available on GitHub).

Technical Skills

- Programming in R
- Multivariate Statistics and Machine Learning Methods
- GIS, Remote Sensing, and LIDAR with Open Source Software, ArcGIS and Google Earth Engine
- Git Version Control System
- Familiarity with Python, Bash, SQL, LaTeX, Markdown, HTML, Stata

Treasurer of the Cornell Herpetological Society.

Docent at Staten Island Zoo.

Extracurricular Workshops Attended

<u>Extracurri</u>	<u>cular Workshops Attended</u>
2016	Conversant Communication Training, Saratoga Springs, NY.
	Software Carpentry Instructor Training, Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK.
2015	Software Carpentry Workshop on Python and Git. Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK.
2014	Open Science for Synthesis workshop on Scientific Computing. Held Jointly at the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, Santa Barbara, CA and the Renaissance Computing Institute, Chapel Hill, NC.
	How to Design Plausible and Useful Scenarios for Modeling Landscape Change. Workshop at the US Regional Association of International Association for Landscape Ecology Meeting, Anchorage, AK.
2013	Nonparametric and Machine Learning Modeling using Open Source Tools: Workflows for Linking GIS with Statistical Software in R. Workshop at the US Regional Association of

International Association for Landscape Ecology Meeting, Austin, TX.